All right, we're going to start. If
I can see this mouse.
בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Wait a second. I do, I have to
leave in
8:20. Hope it stays. Start broadcast.
Very good. All right, so we've been discussing the laws of kings,
royalty in the משנה Mishna and contrasting comparing that to those of
the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So the king is at a higher
status, so that affects things like testifying and one
of the rules is that מלך לא דן ולא דנין אותו. Melech
lo dan v'lo danin oto.
So he apparently gets like what we would call today diplomatic immunity
and he's exempt for what we would say today jury duty, if
you want to look at it that way. Anyway, no he can't
be a judge. Which is funny because שפטנו מלכנו, shefatenu malkenu, right?
That's one of the things that's actually in the משפט המלוכה. Mishpat
HaMelucha. So
which is interesting, but apparently it really means that he's not, he
doesn't participate let's say with the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. You know, he adjudicates
all day long if he wants but that's sort of by royal
fiat as opposed to, you know what I mean, as opposed to
like, all right, let's go through due process as outlined by the
Jewish legal system. So I think that that's kind of what the
idea is. Or maybe it means that he can like sort of
pass his own laws, but he's not like really sitting there judging
cases in that traditional legal way that the סנהדרין Sanhedrin is. So
that's really what it's about. Didn't he actually sit with סנהדרין Sanhedrin
at some point just previous under the משנה? Mishna? And he didn't
adjudicate?
Well, yeah,
I'd have to review that one. Is there a difference between דן
dan and לשפוט? lishpot?
It might be. I mean like, that's what I was trying to
say that it might be that one might be like actually going
through the process of adjudicating a case as opposed to making the
laws. That's what I was trying to say that might be a
difference? I'm just guessing. So you know, that's just shooting off hip
there. Is there a difference between kind of things that affect
the national policy? Yeah, that's a good point. You know, could be
that too. You know, that he may make overarching state laws as
opposed to dealing sitting
adjudicating תורה Torah law, which the law's already there and he just
needs to find out what applies to this particular case. Yeah, you're
right, it could be.
But we're not getting into that right now anyway. So interestingly, אמר
רב יוסף לא שנו אלא מלכי ישראל, Amar Rav Yosef lo shanu
ela Malkhei Yisrael, right? אבל מלכי בית דוד דן ודנין אותו. Aval
Malkhei Beit David dan v'danin oto.
So that depends, you'd think actually that it goes the other way
around. That מלכי דוד Malkhei David would get more of a pass
and מלכי ישראל Malkhei Yisrael would be stricter because מלכי דוד Malkhei
David are two kingdoms they split off from each other and if
you will like the more I guess traditionally legitimate one. I don't
know if that's the right way to look at it, but more
traditionally the traditional one is from the Davidic line. You know, like
דוד, David, שלמה, Shlomo, all those kind of people.
They
actually that this doesn't apply. It's only מלכי ישראל Malkhei Yisrael that
are לא דנין אותו. lo danin oto. But it's because of a
specific מעשה. ma'aseh. So whenever you get to specific instances, specific reasons,
then it just applies oftentimes insofar as just the מעשה ma'aseh encompasses,
which was a מעשה ma'aseh from מלכי בית ישראל Malkhei Beit Yisrael
which we'll get into in just a moment. So how do we
know that it applies to מלכי בית דוד? Malkhei Beit David? דכתיב
בית דוד כה אמר ה' דינו לבקר משפט. De-ketiv Beit David ko
amar Hashem dinu la-boker mishpat. So God says that, well,
לבקר דינו לבקר, la-boker dinu la-boker, sorry, לבקר משפט. la-boker mishpat. Judge
משפט, mishpat, judgment, I guess, law in the morning. So and that
was applying to them. So they kind of are supposed to do
that.
So it doesn't apply to מלכי בית דוד. Malkhei Beit David. ואי
לא דנין ליה היכי דנינן? Ve-i lo danin lei heikhi daninan? So
then okay, that's fine. So that means that he can judge, but
how does it mean how do we learn from there that he
gets judged? Sort of the same way we learned earlier, ואי לא
דנינן ליה היכי דנין? Ve-i lo daninan lei heikhi danin? וכתיב התקוששו
וקושו. Ve-ketiv hitchosheshu va-khoshu. We had this before. So like, you know,
if you're on the giving end you have to be at the
receiving end too. So
התקוששו וקושו. hitchosheshu va-khoshu. So you know, prepare yourself then others so
for תשובה. teshuvah.
So what applies to them applies to you. So it works both
ways. אמר ריש לקיש קשוט עצמך ואחר כך קשוט אחרים. Amar Reish
Lakish kshot atzmekha ve-ahar kshot acherim. Like we just said. explained. אלא
מאי איסי מאי טעמא? Ela mai Isai mai ta'ama? Okay fine, so
we know that מלכי בית דוד Malchei Beis David this doesn't apply
in the subjects to be judged and judging others. מאי טעמא? Mai
ta'ama? But why do we, why is our Mishna then that says
that they can't be judged or judge others applying to מלכי ישראל?
Malchei Yisrael? מאי טעמא לא משום מעשה שהיה? Mai ta'ama lo mishum
ma'aseh shehayah?
So there was a specific circumstance שהיה shehayah דעבדיה דינאי מלכא. de-avdeh
de-Yannai Malka.
ינאי מלכא Yannai Malka appears often enough in ש"ס, Shas, and he
appears in conjunction with שמעון בן שטח, Shimon ben Shatach, which I
don't know if this is true or not, but שמעון בן שטח
Shimon ben Shatach was his brother-in-law. So ינאי מלכא, Yannai Malka, I
don't know if that's here or not, but שמעון בן שטח's Shimon
ben Shatach's sister married ינאי, Yannai, I think at least according to
the Sages as far as I remember.
Anyway, so his slave of the king, this king's slave, קטל נפשא.
katal nafsha. So he killed somebody. אמר להו שמעון בן שטח לחכמים:
Amar lehu Shimon ben Shatach lachachamim: תנו עיניכם בו ונדוננו. Tnu eineichem
bo venidunenu. All right, well you know, he killed someone, he needs
to be judged, you know, you need a סנהדרין Sanhedrin of twenty-three.
שלחו ליה, Shalchu leh, they sent to King Yannai, עבדך קטל נפשא,
avdach katal nafsha, your servant killed somebody. Then שדריה להו, shadreih lehu,
send him to us, we need to judge him. שלחו ליה, Shalchu
leh,
and then later on actually they said you know what, תא אנת
נמי להכא, ta ant nami lehacha,
you gotta come too, King Yannai, you gotta be here. Why? And
this is a somewhat disturbing comparison because of והועד בבעליו. ve-hu'ad biv'alav.
אמרה תורה יבוא בעל השור ויעמוד על שורו. Amrah Torah yavo ba'al
ha-shor ve-ya'amod al shoro. So if there's a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal,
a case of a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, the שור shor killed
somebody, it becomes a שור הנסקל shor haniskal once it's brought to
court, and the owner has to be there too for the trial.
I don't know exactly what he has to do, but you think
והועד בבעליו, ve-hu'ad biv'alav, you know, if you looked at it from
the פשט pshat case is that he gets warned, you know, and
then he gets warned, he gets warned, and then whatever happens you
judge the שור. shor. You don't need the בעלים be'alim there. But
apparently והועד בבעליו, ve-hu'ad biv'alav,
the owner of the ox has to be there for the trial.
So we're saying the עבד eved is no different than the ox.
Again, a disturbing comparison, but what we really mean by that is
if someone's money damages somebody, the owner has to be there for
this, so the slave is your money, so you need to be
there for the trial. So again, what the parameters of that are
is not for this time. We use that concept in US court
law today, that what if your dog kills somebody or if your
employee runs over somebody, the employer is also liable. Really?
Respondeat superior. It depends if he's doing work, exactly. Yeah.
Okay.
Anyway, so whatever way he has to be involved, he has to
be involved. So
you gotta come too, King Yannai. So fine,
אתא ויתיב, ata ve-yasiv, so he came. Then אמר ליה שמעון בן
שטח, amar leh Shimon ben Shatach, שמעון בן שטח Shimon ben Shatach
said, ינאי המלך עמוד על רגליך ויעידו בך. Yannai HaMelech amod al
raglecha ve-ya'idu bach. All right, stand up,
and then you know we need to testify, whatever that means in
this case, ויעידו בך, ve-ya'idu bach, you know, we need to officially
I guess tell you that your slave killed somebody
and you know and then are you gonna lose out on money
so I guess you know you need to understand the full repercussions
as it affects you.
So you know, he seems like a little bit imperious almost here,
עמוד על רגליך, amod al raglecha, but he does say ינאי המלך.
Yannai HaMelech. You know, because it says ועמדו שני האנשים אשר להם
הריב לפני ה'. ve-amdu shnei ha-anashim asher lahem ha-riv lifnei Hashem. They
have to, the witnesses have to stand up when they testify. So
ולא לפנינו אתה עומד אלא לפני מי שאמר והיה העולם אתה עומד.
ve-lo lifneinu atah omed ela lifnei mi she-amar vehayah ha-olam atah omed.
It's not really for us, he's sort of like backtracking, in other
words we're not saying this, you stand up in order to show
like oh we're the judges and we're so you know powerful and
honorable and you gotta stand because we're here. It's not because of
us, it's because of God, because God is always you know ultimately
the backdrop for all these court cases. שנאמר ועמדו שני האנשים אשר
להם הריב לפני ה', Shene'emar ve-amdu shnei ha-anashim asher lahem ha-riv lifnei
Hashem, right, that's the part that's missing. So you gotta just, you're
really there because of God. So אמר ליה, amar leh, then ינאי
המלך Yannai HaMelech said to שמעון בן שטח, Shimon ben Shatach, לא
כשתאמר אתה אלא כמה שיאמרו חבריך. lo keshetomar atah ela kemah sheyomru
chaveirecha. So all right fine, but I'm not gonna go based on
what you're saying, I want you know some sort of a consensus
or you know what your colleagues are gonna say.
Okay, so turn the page, נפנה לימינו. nifneh liyimino. So then שמעון
בן שטח Shimon ben Shatach turned to the right, וכבשו פניהם בקרקע.
ve-chavshu pneihem bakarka. So you know, look,
if the king is there like the judges are potentially somewhat cowed,
and so the judges, you know, looked down, right, וכבשו פניהם בקרקע,
ve-chavshu pneihem bakarka, sort of like the ostrich burying his head in
the sand kind of thing. So וכבשו פניהם בקרקע, ve-chavshu pneihem bakarka,
so all right, they didn't say anything. נפנה לשמאלו וכבשו פניהם בקרקע.
nifneh lismolo ve-chavshu pneihem bakarka. So same thing happened. Then שמעון בן
שטח Shimon ben Shatach turned to the left and you know the
judges sort of looking the other way. אמר להם שמעון בן שטח
בעלי מחשבות אתם. Amar lahem Shimon ben Shatach ba'alei machshavot atem. You're
just like you know, you're just thinking, right, but you're not doing
anything, you're just like sitting there pondering.
It could be, or it can
mean... יבוא בעל המחשבות, Yavo Ba'al Hamachshavot,
so the
ultimate reader of thoughts, which is
God, ויפרע מכם, veyifra mikem, and exact his just deserts on you
guys who were doing nothing in this case. מיד בא גבריאל וחבטן
בקרקע ומתו. Miyad ba Gavriel vechavatan bakarka vametu.
So גבריאל המלאך Gavriel hamalach came and just killed them basically, the
judges. ואותה שעה אמרו מלך לא דן ולא דנין אותו לא מעיד
ולא מעידין אותו. Ve'otah sha'ah amru melech lo dan velo danin oto
lo meyiv velo meyivin oto.
So
all right, that does it. So no more court cases regarding the
king. I mean, you'd think if that really was the reason, it
shouldn't be מלכי בית דוד malkei beit David either, but again you
have a פסוק pasuk which seems to say that they really are
part of the court process. And of course we know, oftentimes we
just sort of only narrowly interpret the מעשה שהיה, ma'aseh shehayah, especially
if we don't really want to expand it just for the circumstances
that engendered it. And anyway, so that was the reason. What a
strange case, because you would think it would be something relative to
the king, but it was just this עבד. eved.
But I guess that makes it even stronger, right? Because it was
just this sort of like their... because of property, so to speak,
right? And even that was too much. But I guess the point
is that when a king doesn't want to appear, the judges are
sufficiently afraid that you're not going to have good justice anyway, then
it's sort of what's the point of the whole thing?
So by the way, to your question, and I knew there was
an answer to this, David, let's go back to י"ט עמוד א'
yud tet amud aleph on the תוספות. Tosafot. Let's do one or
two of them. אבל מלכי בית דוד דנין אותו. Aval malkei beit
David danin oto. ויש לומר היכי יכול לדון והא רמינן לעיל אין
מושיבין מלך בסנהדרין. Veyesh lomar haichi yachol ladun vehar'aminan l'eil ein moshivin
melech besanhedrin. Right? So how can the king even be, he said
he can judge and judges others, I'm on the third תוספות Tosafot
on י"ט עמוד א'. yud tet amud aleph. So how can that
happen, right? You don't put a מלך melech in the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin,
דכתיב לא תענה על ריב, de'chtiv lo ta'aneh al riv,
don't, which we interpret to mean don't second guess a רב, rav,
the מופלא שבבית דין, mufla shebebeit din, the important guy in the
בית דין. beit din. ויש לומר דהכא מיירי דווקא לדון דיני ממונות.
Veyesh lomar dehacha mairi davka ledun dinei mamonot. This is just דיני
ממונות. dinei mamonot. ולא איכפת לן אם לא יכולן לחלוק אחריו Velo
ichpat lan im lo yecholan lachlok acharav because ממונות mamonot
is, the stakes aren't as high, so people feel I guess less
hesitant
to go after the king and even if it means to contradict
him. אם כן בדיני נפשות מתחילין מן הקטן, Im kein be'dinei nefashot
matchilin min hakatan, just in a regular court case, even the most
elder senior knowledgeable member of the בית דין beit din can start
out with what he thinks the verdict is.
Then he asks a question about another case of a specific case
and he answers it. But anyway, so it just, I guess it
depends what kind of court case it is. So you may not
be in דיני נפשות, dinei nefashot,
this may not apply. So A. Then B, there's the next תוספות
ינאי המלך. Tosafot Yannai hamamelech. The next one,
I'm not going to read the whole תוספות, Tosafot, but he tries
to compare like the תלמיד חכם talmid chacham and the מלך. melech.
Meaning like a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham doesn't have to stand up,
right, when if he's, so why does the מלך melech have to
stand up? You'd think קל וחומר kal vachomer the מלך melech was
the most exalted of the nation. So this is a very nice,
let me get more for the answer. So I think it's just
a very nice concept.
So just go to ויש לומר veyesh lomar which is in the
middle of the תוספות Tosafot and in the middle of the line
in which it appears. ויש לומר דוודאי עשה
דכבוד תורה עדיף. Veyesh lomar de'vadai asei de'kvod torah adif. So, meaning
his whole premise was תלמיד חכם talmid chacham doesn't have to stand
so קל וחומר kal vachomer king. So he's saying that's not really
the way it is because תורה Torah is better in that regard.
ואם כן אף על פי שאין תלמיד חכם צריך לעמוד ינאי היה
צריך לעמוד. Ve'im kein af al pi she'ein talmid chacham tzarich la'amod,
Yannai hayah tzarich la'amod. ינאי Yannai had to stand up even though
תלמיד חכם talmid chacham would not. והאי תלמיד חכם יכול למחול על
כבודו. V'hai talmid chacham yachol limchol al kevodo.
What do you mean like there's a concept that the תלמיד חכם
talmid chacham can be מוחל mochel on his כבוד kavod but a
מלך melech can't. So what do you mean, so why would a
תלמיד חכם talmid chacham not have to stand but a מלך melech
would? Because he says,
why can't a מלך? melech? Because it says שום תשים עליך מלך
שתהא אימתו עליך. som tasim alecha melech she'tehei eimato alecha. That's what
we but here's what I wanted to get to. כי כבודו, Ki
kevodo, the כבוד kavod of a מלך melech בא
לו משום דמצוות המקום כך הוא. ba lo mishum de'mitvat hamakom kach
hu. So meaning it's not intrinsic. It's extrinsic because God says you
have to honor the king. He's eventually inherited but it
doesn't, it's not because of him so much, right? It just descends,
it comes because your father was the king, so it's not because
of you, right? Meaning the first one, but ואינו יכול להפקיע מצוות
המקום. ve'eino yachol l'hafkiah mitvat hamakom.
So since it's not coming from you, it comes from God,
you have no say in that. אבל, Aval, this is the punchline
about תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, תורתו דיליה. torato dilei. You get it
because of yourself, your own accomplishments. You've learned תורה, Torah, you've struggled,
you've put in the time, תורה Torah becomes yours, you've acquired it.
It says ותורתו. ve'torato. We'll get to that. Actually, that's the end
of the תוספות. Tosafot. Okay. So therefore since the תורה Torah is
yours, יכול למחול היה על כבודו. yachol limchol hayah al kevodo. You
earned it. So therefore you can relinquish it as appropriate. שלו היא.
shelo hi. כדילהלן. kedelahalan. בתחילה נקראת על שמו של הקדוש ברוך הוא,
bitechilah nikret al shemo shel hakadosh baruch hu, ולבסוף נקראת על שמו.
ulevasof nikret al shemo.
In the beginning the תורה Torah is called on the name of
God, but at the end it's named after the, you know, name.
It's, you know, viewed as your, once you've learned it, שנאמר, shene'emar,
כי אם בתורת השם חפצו ובתורתו יהגה יומם ולילה. ki im betorat
Hashem cheftzo uvetorato yehgeh yomam valaylah. If its חפץ, cheftz, his desire
is in תורת השם, Torat Hashem, and then ובתורתו uvetorato which you
would think refers to הקדוש ברוך הוא Hakadosh Baruch Hu and in
God's תורה Torah you will learn day and night, no. What it
means is first the first part, תורת השם. Torat Hashem. And then
once you have it, ובתורתו, uvetorato, your own תורה, Torah, you'll be
reviewing night and day. So anyway, the point is that a מלך
melech would have to, you know, that there's differences between a תלמיד
חכם talmid chacham and a מלך. melech. Which is, that's really what
I just wanted to get to, that it's just nice, you know,
that there's a difference between earned accomplishments
and, you know, accomplishments that just, or מעלות ma'alot status that you
just got. Okay, that was
a דעה, de'oh, that was a judging. לא חליצה ולא חולצין. lo
chalitzah velo choltzin.
No חליצה, chalitzah, not involved in that process. תניא, אבל אמר רב
אשי, tanya, aval amar Rav Ashi, אפילו מאן דאמר נשיא שמחל על
כבודו, כבודו מחול, מלך שמחל על כבודו, אין כבודו מחול. afilu man
d'amar nasi shemachal al kevodo, kevodo machul, melech shemachal al kevodo, ein
kevodo machul. So apparently for, you know, the חליצה chalitzah is viewed
as somewhat demeaning, especially since there's spitting involved and she has to
spit not at him, but you know like in front of him,
in his direction on the ground. So so this doesn't seem to
be such a מכובד mechubad thing. So you know, as we're saying
a minute ago, right? That a מלך'ס כבוד, melech's kavod, he you
know has to adhere to. מלך שמחל על כבודו אין כבודו מחול,
melech shemachal al kevodo ein kevodo machul, שנאמר שום תשים עליך מלך
שאימתו עליך, shene'emar som tasim alecha melech she'eimato alecha, the פסוק pasuk
that we've been quoting, you have to appoint a king onto you
and you know,
עליך, alecha, his אימה eimah has to be on you, he has
to like you know sort of view him as being on you
at all points in time, which means that you know you can't
make light of his כבוד. kavod. So okay fine. But מצווה שאני.
mitzvah shani. Okay, that maybe that's in other cases, but when there's
a מצווה mitzvah to do it, you gotta do it, even the
king has to do מצוות. mitzvot. So that is that,
that is that position. Let me just see something in the משנה.
Mishnah.
That was the תנא קמא'ס Tanna Kamma's position. רבי יהודה אומר אם
רצה לחלוץ או לייבם, לזכור לטוב, Rabbi Yehudah omer im ratzah lachlotz
o l'yabbem, l'zachur latov, right? That was the dissenting opinion. So he
doesn't have to do it, but you know it'd be nice if
he did. So
so that was obviously the other opinion, right? So you know,
the first opinion says obviously don't, you know, for that reason, שאימתו
עליך. she'eimato alecha. Then the other opinion that says לזכור לטוב l'zachur
latov is because מצווה שאני. mitzvah shani.
That's that's why. ואין נושאים. ve'ein nos'im.
Similarly, you do not marry his widow. That's the end, towards the
end of the משנה. Mishnah. רבי יהודה אומר נושא מלך אלמנתו של
מלך. Rabbi Yehudah omer nosei melech almenato shel melech. One king can
marry the widow of another, presumably his predecessor. שכן מצינו בדוד שנשא
אלמנתו של שאול. sheken matzinu b'David shenasa almenato shel Shaul. דוד David
married the אלמנה almanah of שאול, Shaul, שנאמר ואתנה לך את בית
אדוניך, shene'emar ve'etnah l'cha et beit adonecha, I'm translating it literally, I
will give you the house of your master, ואת נשי אדוניך בחיקך
ve'et neshei adonecha b'cheikecha and the wives
or women
of your master in your lap, right? Which is typically viewed as
wives, right? Because you know, as they say, אשת חיקו, eshet cheiko,
like that's that's other פסוקים pesukim from the תורה, Torah, you know,
the your wives lie in your lap or you lie in her
lap, whatever, sense of intimacy.
So now be aware that in the the ancient world, like you
know, one of the
prime signs of, or that you would demonstrated,
you know, that you are now usurping the throne or you're the
king is you would take the פילגשים pilegeshim and the wives of
the of your predecessor.
You know, that that does, that's like, you know, and that's a
sure sign of rebellion if you're doing that.
You know, that's at the beginning. That in the ancient, that was
a sign, taking your you know the prior king or the current
king's wives shows your rebellion if you if you were to do
that, that's like a coup. Those are like those are fighting words,
right? So that was you know, that's what אבשלום Avshalom tried to
do, right? He
tried to take a... do you remember who אבישג השונמית Avishag Hashunamit
was? דוד המלך David Hamelech was old, 70 years old, you know,
that was considered the end of the life span, ויכסהו בבגדים ולא
יחם לו, v'yichasuhu begadim velo yecham lo, he never could, he never
could... we read this as a הפטרה, haftarah, you know, he never
was able to be warm. They in search you know, then they
searched through all ישראל Yisrael for like a young you know lady
apparently who was viewed as having like a lot of heat because
you're young and... you know I have a teenager daughter like she's
always hot, I mean it's like you know probably something to that.
I'm like I'm like freezing, she's like I'm boiling. You know so
there's something about kids this age I noticed this. So like I'm
like wear a coat, you know, so... Young people got it and
boys? Well yeah I guess so I don't know my... but
but anyway so like you know so she sat, she was always
sitting in his lap but you know he didn't have relations with
her but but that אבשלום Avshalom tried you know when he rebelled
he wanted you know he tried taking her as a you know...
anyway so you know so anyway the point was דוד David was
clearly replacing שאול Shaul so you could say that that was you
know a reason to do that right but in a normal you
know line of
succession... I didn't have access to it. But we're going to go
through
what this means and then we're going to try to understand דוד
המלך David HaMelech who married the or did he that's what we're
going to go through the daughters of שאול Shaul right? He had
two שאול Shaul had two daughters anyone remember their names? מרב Merav
and מיכל. Michal. Right. One was older one was younger they weren't
twins. So the question was and also but they were the daughters
of the wife though? Well no these are שאול שאול's Shaul Shaul
daughters. Right but we said... No I'm just telling you I'm telling
I know I know we're going to get that I'm just telling
you what we're going to get what the גמרא Gemara is going
to go through. He's going to דוד David because this is a
פסוק pasuk by דוד David and
then then how he was or wasn't married to the daughters of
שאול Shaul then if you also remember שאול Shaul sort of took
them away from דוד David and gave them to other men right?
So how could he do that right? And how can he marry
two sisters right? And also the daughter of a wife that's what
I was trying to... and then and then we're going to get
to all that so daughter of a mother is the same.
Well that we won't... that won't
be... okay anyway.
So as I mentioned or as the משנה Mishnah mentioned really that
this was a מחלוקת machloket in the משנה Mishnah of whether you
can marry the widow of a king. So the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma said no רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says yes if it's a
king marrying the widow of a king not a commoner.
And he cited a פסוק pasuk which we'll have to contend to.
So
okay so what's the response right? I mean רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
brought a פסוק. pasuk. How do you argue against a פסוק? pasuk?
So again what I said is that that might be a one-time
thing because this is a different dynasty whereas if it's just if
it's the same dynasty then no.
So they said תני אמרו לו לרבי יהודה tanni amru lo lerabbi
yehuda the response is נשים אתן לך מבית
המלך. nashim eten lecha mibeit hamelech. So ומני הוא u'mani hu מרב
ומיכל. Merav u'Michal. So it doesn't so when it says this specific
פסוק pasuk that I will give you
the נשי מלך nishei melech it can mean like wives right? Like
אשתי ishti so my wives נשי nashai right? Whatever. Or it can
mean as in נשים nashim women. So again it totally doesn't sound
like that and I don't think anyone would interpret this interpret this
that way if you were to look at it at first at
least first blush. Right בית אדוניך beit adonecha is his possessions נשי
אדוניך בחיקך nishei adonecha bicheikecha in your
I
mean you'd think it means you'd think it means wives instead of
daughters what's the big deal about that? Right so no but נשים
nashim he's they're interpreting it to mean just
women. Not the wives because that's not allowed but rather the women
you'll be you'll marry the other not the wives whoever else it
was. In
this
case we're saying מרב ומיכל. Merav u'Michal. So now that now that
we're up to that now we're going to discuss them. But wait
a minute I just have a question right? Yes. If we're putting
this in the context of
somebody taking over a kingship and then marrying the wife for example
and then we're saying it's the daughters right?
But שאול Shaul said that he would give... oh I know we're
going to get to that. Yeah. So it's not like he's doing
it... oh I know of course like it's totally this sort of
completely blunt blunts the impact of this. Yeah and we're going to
get to that. שמע מיצה דברי רבי יוסי shama mitsa divrei rabbi
yosei היך נשא דוד שתי אחיות בחייהן eich nasa david shtei achayot
bechayeihen right? מיכל Michal and מרב Merav were sisters.
I guess I don't remember like how quick how much it goes
through the lineage maybe you could say different whatever but no
sisters. So answer one אמר ליה מיכל אחר מות מרב נשאה. amar
lei michal achar mot merav nasa. The problem is marrying two sisters
while they're both alive well okay one was married after the other
died.
So רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha אומר קידושי טעות
היו לו במרב omer kiddushei taut hayu lo bemerav no okay so
answer one is it wasn't the same time right? Answer two is
you have to say either it didn't happen at the same time
or he wasn't married to two of them at the same time
right? I mean he wasn't married to two of them while they're
alive. Alive. So there was a problem with the קידושין kiddushin of
one of them so he wasn't actually married to one of them.
So he was only married to one right? So those are the
two answers. קידושי טעות היו לו במרב kiddushei taut hayu lo bemerav
שנאמר תנה את אשתי את מיכל אשר ארסתי לי במאה ערלות פלשתים.
shene'emar tena et ishti et michal asher erasti li beme'ah orlot pelishtim.
So give me my wife מיכל Michal that I betrothed במאה ערלות
פלשתים beme'ah orlot pelishtim that was שאול Shaul made a תנאי tnai
if you want my daughter go ahead and smite these give me
a hundred foreskins of the פלשתים pelishtim and that's what he did.
So מאי תלמודא mai talmuda why is he saying אשתי את מיכל?
et ishti et michal? אמר פפא מיכל אשתי ולא מרב אשתי amar
pappa michal ishti lo merav ishti right? I'm saying מיכל Michal my
wife which means מיכל Michal my wife and
not מרב Merav my wife so
that... falls away.
So מאי קדושי טעות, mai kiddushei ta'ut, so what was what's the
background here? דכתיב והיה האיש אשר יכנו יעשרנו המלך עשר גדול. dichtiv
vehaya ha'ish asher yakenu ya'asrenu hamelech osher gadol. So this he was
talking about this was with Goliat. So
he was saying that there's a whole פסוק, pasuk, they said, "Oh,
do you see this guy, he's coming to mock
the all the Jewish people?" And then the king is saying "whoever
manages to overcome this guy, then be very rich and
and there's this whole part and then also the king's he'll give
the king the king will give his daughter to this person as
a wife, right?" So that's how that whole started and then of
course who won, David won, so that's how this this started. So
okay על כל פנים. al kol panim. So so he did, right?
He killed Goliat. So now he has this עשר גדול, osher gadol,
right? So what David said is "Alright, with the money that you
would have given me I'm going to use that as" because of
course you have to do קדושין, kiddushin, right? You have to do
קדושין kiddushin is כסף שטר ביאה kesef shtar biah so
כסף. kesef. So David said, "Okay, the money you would have given
me, take
that," right? אבל הוספה aval hosafa with
that, אמר לו מלוה יש לי גביך המקדש במלוה אינה מקודשת. amar
lo milve yesh li gavach hamikadesh bemilve eina mekudeshet. So the idea
is that it wasn't his own money yet, right? If David had
taken the money and then given it back, then it would have
been fine. But he never had the money, right? So that's the
question. So if you say that this is the קדושי טעות, kiddushei
ta'ut, if you say you can't do that, you can't just relinquish
money you never
had as a bridal price, then you take that side of the
position,
then then it never works so he's never married to her.
So but if he or but if you take the side that
either something else happened, he did קדושין kiddushin that's not mentioned in
the תורה Torah and I mean in נביאים Nevi'im then he was.
Or if you say that this is not a problem then she
was. So that could be the נקודת המחלוקת. nekudat hamachlokes. That could
be the reason why. Anyway, so this viewpoint is saying that that's
that he betrothed her with with this money that would have been
due to him and that's doesn't count. So
that's that position. אבל יהביה לאדריאל. aval yahveih l'Adriel. Okay, so what
did שאול Shaul do? So he gave he gave
her he betrothed her whatever, gave it as a wife to this
אדריאל. Adriel. דכתיב ויהי בעת תת את
מרב בת שאול לדוד והיא נתנה לאדריאל המחלתי לאשה. dichtiv vayehi be'et
tet et Merav bat Shaul leDavid vehia nitna l'Adriel haMechollati l'isha. So
she was given to this guy אדריאל. Adriel. אמר ליה. amar lei.
So then the story continues. אמר ליה אי בעית דאיתן לך מיכל
זיל אייתי לי מאה ערלות פלשתים, amar lei i bayit d'eitan lach
Michal zil aiti li me'ah orlot Plishtim, right? So that that comes
next. In other words okay didn't get her with the what happened
to the Goliat, right? Then he gave her to אדריאל. Adriel. He
says, "Alright, fine, you really want her? So now you got to
do something else. You got to kill these hundred פלשתים, Plishtim, these
hundred Philistines, and give me their foreskins." So he did. אייתי לי
מאה ערלות פלשתים אייתי ליה. aiti li me'ah orlot Plishtim aiti lei.
So alright killed them, brought them to him. אמר ליה מלוה ופרוטה
אית לך גבאי. amar lei milve upruta it lach gavai. So okay
fine, so had the מלוה milve from before, right? All this money
that you would have given me and a פרוטה. pruta. So okay
he like "Here's a million dollars and like three cents," right? So
or you can say, "Here's a million dollars and like a hundred
foreskins." Here's the מלוה milve and the פרוטה. pruta. He asked for
a hundred and he gave him two hundred.
Oh yeah that's right. Right. Right. Anyway here are all the foreskins
go have fun, right?
So the foreskins are the שוה פרוטה? shaveh pruta? Right yeah it
could be. Either he actually
came out with a פרוטה pruta of his own and said, "The
million dollars
that you would have owed me from killing Goliat and here,
here's the gum in my
pocket," or or here are the foreskins.
I think it really is referring to the foreskins, a פרוטה pruta
that's worth something, right? So
anyway, שויוה מלוה ופרוטה דעתיה
אמלוה. shavyah milve upruta da'ateih amilve. So alright like the million dollars
and the foreskins, okay what are you going to think is the
main thing affecting the קדושין? kiddushin? The million dollars, right? So but
then the problem is this is money David never had, that's why
the קדושין kiddushin never worked, right? So מלוה ופרוטה דעתיה אמלוה דעתיה
אמלוה ופרוטה דעתיה אפרוטה. milve upruta da'ateih amilve da'atya amilve upruta da'atya
apruta. You mentioned the it's the last thing you mentioned,
the מלוה milve and the פרוטה. pruta. Maybe even דעתיה אמלוה da'ateih
amilve or only דעתיה אפרוטה, da'atya apruta, which is why by the
way what we do under the חופה, chuppah, right?
Why can't we just say give this huge diamond ring under the
חופה, chuppah, right?
As opposed to giving a simple gold ring. So we
say
like okay like not because... So if you have in mind a
certain amount of money, you know, she may think, oh, this is
like a ten thousand dollar ring and it turns out it's like,
you know, cheap knockoff cubic zirconium, it's worth like fifty nine ninety
nine you got on the internet. By the way, cubic zirconium can
actually be really expensive by the way. But they get like good
quality.
So if the woman is thinking a certain amount and it's not
that way, you know, then it might, as people say, it might
not really be a good קידושין kiddushin even if though it's worth,
according, there's no question that it's worth more than a פרוטה, prutah,
right? Which is why then we, you know, we do something as
simple, like you know, she's not thinking it's worth like ten thousand
dollars. So, I mean, not that's the exact same thing, but that's,
I'm just throwing that in there as a related concept.
So and then of course they ask the, you know, we ask
עדים edim is this worth a פרוטה, prutah, right? So we know
like, you know, we're מקדש mikadesh you in a minimal amount to
avoid these questions.
So,
so Shaul was saying, okay, the מלווה, milveh, and the מלווה milveh
was, you know, the money that he would have given him, we
can't do that since the money he never had. So דעתה דמלווה
ודעתה דארבע מאה פרוטה דעתה דפרוטה. da'ata d'milveh v'da'ata d'arba me'ah prutah
da'ata d'prutah. That's one way of explaining it. So that's why מדין
קידושי טעות, m'din kiddushei ta'ot, right? David thought it was good but
it wasn't. אי בעית אימא דכולי עלמא מלוה פרוטה דעתה דפרוטה. iy
ba'it eima d'kuli alma milveh prutah da'ata d'prutah. And we say that
everyone holds that that would be okay. Shaul סבר savar לא חזי
למידי. lo chazi l'midei. Okay, the hundred foreskins is not worth anything.
It's not even a פרוטה. prutah. Like what are we going to
do with a hundred foreskins, right? Two hundred foreskins. But David סבר
savar חזו ליה, chazu lei, חבי לשונרא, chavi l'shunrei, feed it to
the cats and dogs, so you know, you have a household, you
know, pets, whatever, household beasts, you know, okay, you would have had
to feed them something, you would have had to throw them meat,
meat's worth something, instead throw them a hundred foreskins. All right. So
it's worth something. We also say הי hi and then Shaul was
thinking הינא. hina. ורבי יוסי האי תנא אשת מיכל מאי דריש ביה?
v'Rabbi Yose hai tanna eshet Michol mai darish bei? Okay, so remember
we said that so one said that you, you know,
remember there were two opinions, right? Either you said that one died
before and that's why it wasn't at the you know while they
were both alive or you say that, you know, one קידושין kiddushin
didn't work and it wasn't married to two sisters. By the way
he wasn't married to two sisters
during their lifetimes.
So we just we were just trying to prove that this meant
that that you know those קידושי טעות, kiddushei ta'ot, right? So according
to רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose he says no, he marr- you know,
he married one and then she died and then married the other,
so what do you do with this פסוק pasuk which seems to
say, oh, this one is my wife and not the other? Obviously
you could just say, I mean, my wife, you know, he's just
being very specific, like יעקב Yaakov said רחל בתך הקטנה, Rachel bitcha
haktana, right? So he's saying the same thing. But, you know, so
if you're going to, so what are you going to do to
get out of this
פסוק? pasuk? רבי יוסי לטעמיה דתניא רבי יוסי היה דורש מקראות מעורבבין.
Rabbi Yose l'ta'amei d'tanya Rabbi Yose haya doresh mikra'ot m'rubavin.
He's saying, okay, you know, like מקראות מעורבבין mikra'ot m'rubavin means sort
of like mixed פסוקים pesukim meaning you can interpret it different ways.
That's that's basically that's basically the answer the גמרא Gemara is going
to give. It's sort of like, you know, sort of like a
patch and paste, you know, cut and and to make it make
sense of what we want it to say. דכתיב ויקח המלך את
שני בני רצפה בת איה אשר ילדה לשאול את ארמני ואת מפיבשת
d'ichtiv vayikach hamelech et shnei bnei Ritzpah bat Ayah asher yalda l'Shaul
et Armoni v'et Mephiboshet and we're going through נביאים Nevi'im here. ואת
חמשת בני מיכל אשר ילדה לעדריאל המחלתי v'et chameshet bnei Michol asher
yalda l'Adriel ham'cholati
and the five children of מיכל Michol that she bore to עדריאל
המחלתי. Adriel ham'cholati. Wait a minute, if we're paying attention. Right. It
was the other one, מירב, Merav, right? What do you mean חמשת
בני מיכל? chameshet bnei Michol? מירב Merav was given to עדריאל המחלתי.
Adriel ham'cholati. מיכל Michol was given to, anyone remember? Points if you
remember this. פלטיאל בן ליש, Phaltiel ben Laish, פלטיאל בן ליש. Phaltiel
ben Laish. So, didn't the תורה Torah say she never had children?
We're going to get to that. Yes, we're going to get to
that. Very good. So so you've been reading at some point. וכי
לעדריאל נתנה ולא לפלטיאל בן ליש נתנה, v'chi l'Adriel nitna v'lo l'Phaltiel
ben Laish nitna, right?
You're mix- you're mixing up daughters and men, right? One was given
to, you know, you put the wrong husband with the wrong daughter,
right? So she wasn't given to עדריאל, Adriel, she was given to
פלטיאל בן ליש. Phaltiel ben Laish. דכתיב שאול נתן את מיכל בתו
אשת דוד לפלטיאל בן ליש. d'ichtiv Shaul natan et Michol bito eshet
David l'Phaltiel ben Laish. So מקיש קידושי מירב לעדריאל לקידושי מיכל לפלטי
makish kiddushei Merav l'Adriel l'kiddushei Michol l'Phalti מה קידושי מיכל לפלטי בעבירה
אף קידושי מירב לעדריאל בעבירה. mah kiddushei Michol l'Phalti ba'aveirah af kiddushei
Merav l'Adriel ba'aveirah.
So that's how he gets out of it. Like, you know, it
it shouldn't have happened, you know,
like
why shouldn't have happened? because she was already married. That's what he's
saying. אשת מיכל eshet Michol so meaning the one said that my
my wife מיכל Michol which means the other one isn't? No, you,
yes, they're compared, it was it shouldn't have happened, right? You know,
and that's how we're comparing it. We're not comparing it, you know,
we're and that's exactly why he's saying this one to the other.
You know, neither of them should have happened. Like it's like, you
know, the man with the wrong woman, like you know, you can't
be married to somebody else's wife, so she was married to somebody
else's wife. That's what he's that's what it's trying to say. Who's
the somebody else? דוד's David wife. So you know, none of these
marriages should have been. מה קידושי מיכל לפלטי בעבירה אף קידושי מירב
לעדריאל בעבירה mah kiddushei Michol l'Phalti ba'aveirah af kiddushei Merav l'Adriel ba'aveirah
she should have been married to דוד. David. So then that means
that proves the point that it was that it was valid.
So shouldn't have happened but it was, you know, but meaning that
דוד's David ma- the point, דוד David was married to. to them,
right? That's so therefore since since דוד David was married to them,
you have to say that, you know, one died. Right? That's what
he's that's what he's trying to say. And then by saying if
you see it this way, you know, and it's trying to say
like she's my wife. What are you doing, you know? So she's
already married and you know, and that other פסוק pasuk is proving
that that like you know that שאול Shaul did an עבירה averah
by giving you know this woman
who's my daughter, giving his daughter to somebody else. So that makes
sense, sort of there? Okay. Yes, but when they say she's my
wife, he means that she should be my wife? No, she really
is my wife. Actually a marriage in other words and then he
took her away to give her to somebody else. Yeah, I mean
again like you know just remember like even if they didn't like
live together, husband and wife, you know if you're if you do
אירוסין, erusin, you're still the still the wife, right? So you know
even if you get into that. So
you need again all that, right? So we don't have that anymore
but... okay, so anyway so that's the point. So so that's רב
יוסי, Reb Yosi, that's what רב יוסי Reb Yosi says, you know
they one had to die because דוד David was really married to
both and then you know the other opinion is saying no, he
wasn't married because of קידושי טעות kiddushei ta'ut for whatever reason we
just said, right? You know that the ערלות orlot weren't worth anything
or the מלווה, milveh, you know all that kind of stuff. So
however it is we you know we can explain it.
Okay.
Maybe that's why there's an extra 100. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua right
yeah. רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha okay so now
what what do we do with this?
So just want to say something. Let me just get to I
just this
one
this like another just
lines two
three we were just going to... okay, so now רבי יהושע בן
קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha נמי nami כתיב וחמשת בני מיכל בת
שאול vachamesha benei Michal bat Shaul and she you
know so what
do you
do about that? אמר לה Amar lah רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua וכי
מיכל ילדה והלא מרב ילדה. vechi Michal yaldah halo Merav yaldah. Right?
So again what we did from that פסוק pasuk is that we
tried to compare like oh just like this was a עבירה averah
so too was the other עבירה averah that's which means we prove
that you know in terms of the פסוקים pesukim to say that
what דוד David was saying was he was married to both of
them, right? So how does how does this other one
get out of it? How does רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Korcha saying? So he's saying but but this doesn't make sense
anyway, right? Like again we mixed and matched the wrong woman with
the wrong man.
וכי מיכל ילדה והלא מרב ילדה. vechi Michal yaldah halo Merav yaldah.
מרב Merav had these kids, not מיכל, Michal, so why are we
saying these five kids are
מיכל's? Michal מרב ילדה מיכל גידלה, Merav yaldah Michal giddelah, which is
what you were saying. וכך נקראו על שמה. Vekach nikreu al shemah.
Yeah she died you know and then her aunt you know raised
these orphans.
So and that's why they're called on her name. ללמדך שכל המגדל
יתום בתוך ביתו מעלה עליו הכתוב כאילו ילדו. Lelamedcha shekol hamigadel yatom
betoch beito ma'aleh alav hakatuv keilu yelado. So if you raise and
we're going to expand this, if you raise an orphan in your
home it's as if you bore them. So they're like considered your
children and then we're going to say not just that, as if
you teach them תורה Torah if whatever we're going to expand that.
We're going to expand that. It's not just literally raising an orphan
but supporting somebody maybe, you know, so we'll get to that. So
yeah you had a question?
Not a question, two comments. One, how like the Rabbis they can't
just say that's what he did, you know? They like struggle to...
Oh you're going to see even more of that. I know some.
And then the other thing, it's even more striking here, it's striking
just reading the תנ"ך, Tanakh, is the parallel between לבן, Lavan, יעקב,
Ya'akov, רחל, Rachel, לאה, Leah, and דוד, David, שאול, Shaul, מרב, Merav,
מיכל. Michal. And it's just gets more and more interesting if you
think
about it. Yeah that's very good. I like that. Good point. The
father, the whatever, and then doubling what he has to pay for
the wife that he really wants and not giving her and getting
the one with the kids and the one without the kids and
there's a lot of... I did, yeah, that's exactly what... I did
not
do
that. Okay. No, I'm serious. Alright we gotta move on because I
have to leave in another like five six minutes.
So רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina
אומר מהכא. omer mehacha. So how do we know that like, you
know, if you raise somebody it's considered yours? ותקראנה לו השכנות שם
לאמר יולד בן לנעמי. Vatikerena lo hashenot shem lemor yulad ben le-Na'omi.
So this was by... רות. Ruth.
Right, this is by רות, Ruth, well רות Ruth had a son,
right? So and...
Yes. So
this is רות's Ruth son, but the השכנות hashenot said יולד בן
לנעמי. yulad ben le-Na'omi. Right, all of a sudden a son was
born to נעמי. Na'omi. Now why do you think that actually is?
I would what I would say... what? Because it's an heir or
like... No I mean I think I think what the stigma was,
רות Ruth was a מואביה, Moaviyah, right? So we don't want to
say oh this is the Moabite
kid, right? So let's sweep it under the rug and say this
is the Israelite kid, right? So I think I think that's what's
really going on, personally, but anyway so what we're... So, or, so
you know, what we're saying is נעמי ילדה? Naomi yalada? No, רות
ילדה, Ruth yalada, רות ילדה, Ruth yalada, and נעמי גדלה, Naomi gidla,
ולפיכך נקרא על שמה. u'lefikach nikra al shema. So you know, you
kind of gotta wonder what Ruth was in all this. It's not
like Ruth died, right? You know, in the Midrashim said that Boaz
died, so okay fine, maybe Naomi was helping to raise an orphan,
but the mother was still around, you know, like where was she,
right? So anyway, so apparently she was in the, you know, Naomi's
house. So therefore,
you know, if you raise a kid, even if it's not your
biological child, this is, it's, you know, called after you, meaning, you
know, you're viewed as having gotten this reward or having had children.
רבי יוחנן אמר מהכא, Rabbi Yochanan amar mehacha, another source: ואשתו היהודיה
ילדה את ירד אבי גדור. v'ishto ha'Yehudiyah yalada et Yered avi Gedor.
Now
the timing of this is really crazy.
This is talking about כלב בן יפונה Calev ben Yefuneh according to
the way we're interpreting this, who married אשתו היהודיה, Ishto ha'Yehudiyah, who
married בתיה בת פרעה. Bitya bat Paroh. Yeah.
But chronology is crazy, right? Because, because how old was Caleb when
he went to ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? According to... he was שמונים
שנה shemonim shanah as נביא Novi says, right? That he is one
of the מרגלים meraglim and then, you know, God preserved him for
those forty years. So, you know, he said, ככחי אז ככחי עתה,
kechochi az kachochi ata, right? Like, you know, I'm still in the
prime of my life, you know, I have all this vigor. Right?
So משה Moshe was how old when he went to פרעה? Paroh?
משה בן שמונים שנה ואהרן בן שלש ושמנים שנה בדברם אל פרעה.
Moshe ben shemonim shanah v'Aharon ben shalosh u'shemonim shanah b'daberam el Paroh.
He was eighty years old and אהרן Aharon was eighty... he was
eighty-three. No, but אל פרעה, el Paroh, when they went to פרעה
Paroh I mean. He was eighty years old. All that happened in
a year, right? So still eighty years old when they left מצרים.
Mitzrayim. So משה Moshe was eighty years old and כלב Calev was
forty years old, so he was twice his age, and this is
בתיה בת פרעה Bitya bat Paroh his mother. So כלב Calev is
then marrying, sort of speak, you know, משה's... Moshe he's marrying like,
you know, כלב Calev is marrying בתיה Bitya who's, you know, must
be at least sixty years older than him and like we don't...
anyway, this whole chronology is like kind of weird. ואשתו היהודיה ילדה
את ירד אבי גדור ואת חבר אבי שוכו, v'ishto ha'Yehudiyah yalada et
Yered avi Gedor v'et Chever avi Socho, all these are viewed as
euphemisms for משה. Moshe. ואת יקותיאל אבי זנוח, v'et Yekutiel avi Zanoach,
all these people. ואלה בני בתיה בת פרעה אשר לקח מרד, v'eleh
b'nei Bitya bat Paroh asher lakach Mered, right?
Okay, מרד. Mered. ומרד, v'Mered, but we can't leave good enough alone,
so we're trying to say מרד Mered is not really מרד, Mered,
which is a weird name, right? Who would you call, you know,
you'd call your kid rebellion? So it means כלב, Calev, who, you
know, was מרד בעצת מרגלים. marad ba'atzat meraglim. So that proves that
if you want to, sort of do all these gyrations with the
timelines and the פסוקים, psukim, that, that, you know, that therefore, okay,
he I guess helped... I don't know what, raise משה? Moshe? Or...
it's weird. אשר לקח לו מרד. asher lakach lo Mered. מרד זה
כלב. Mered zeh Calev. למה נקרא שמו מרד? שמרד בעצת מרגלים. lama
nikra shmo Mered? shemarad ba'atzat meraglim. And then,
okay, why was he called מרד? Mered? Because he rebelled against the
עצת מרגלים. atzat meraglim. Okay. But וכי בתיה ילדה? v'chi Bitya yalada?
Anyway, the point was, the point was that בתיה בת פרעה Bitya
bat Paroh
gave birth, it says, right? To these people: אבי זנוח, אבי שוכו,
avi Zanoach, avi Socho,
all these people.
And it doesn't mean that כלב Calev helped raise him, it could
be that כלב Calev married her a lot later. So, so that
part doesn't, you know, have to be that way. But anyway, he
did marry בתיה בת פרעה Bitya bat Paroh who had all these...
אשתו היהודיה Ishto ha'Yehudiyah who we're saying, you know,
who we're saying is equal to בתיה בת פרעה Bitya bat Paroh
based on the... since they're both in the same פסוק pasuk that
מרד Mered took. So whoever מרד Mered is, the point was though,
you don't even have to go with all that, you just say
that בתיה בת פרעה Bitya bat Paroh gave birth to all these
people, and we're saying they're all משה. Moshe. Right? That's the part
that isn't in there. But,
so
did בתיה Bitya give actually birth to him? No. אלא יוכבד ילדה,
בתיה גדלה, ולפיכך נקרא על שמה. ela Yocheved yalada, Bitya gidla, u'lefikach
nikra al shema. So
בתיה בת פרעה Bitya bat Paroh raised משה, Moshe, so therefore, you
know, she's viewed as his kid. He's viewed as her kid. רבי
אלעזר אמר מהכא, Rabbi Elazar amar mehacha, a different source: גאלת בזרוע
עמך בני יעקב ויוסף סלה. ga'alta bizroa amcha b'nei Yaakov v'Yosef sela.
So בני יעקב ויוסף b'nei Yaakov v'Yosef
are in the same
פסוק. pasuk. Now notice, first we went from, you know, raising an
orphan. Now it's just raising a kid, right? Because, you know, משה
Moshe wasn't orphaned. So now it's בני יעקב
ויוסף. b'nei Yaakov v'Yosef. ויוסף's Yosef in the picture? What do you
mean?
וכי יוסף ילד? v'chi Yosef yalad? No, אלא יעקב ילד ויוסף כילכל.
ela Yaakov yalad v'Yosef kilkel. Because יוסף Yosef supported everybody when they
went down into מצרים. Mitzrayim. So therefore, לפיכך נקראו על שמו. lefikach
nikru al shmo. So now we've even expanded it: raise an orphan,
just to raise, you know, now even just provide for one
also considered yours. אמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן, Amar
Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan, now it's not even supporting
them: כל המלמד בן חבירו תורה, מעלה עליו הכתוב כאילו ילדו. kol
hamelamed ben chavero Torah, ma'aleh alav hakatuv k'ilu yelado. If you
just teach him Torah,
it's as
if you give birth to him. שנאמר: shene'emar: ואלה תולדות אהרן ומשה.
v'eleh toldot Aharon u'Moshe. וכתיב: u'chtiv: ואלה שמות בני אהרן. v'eleh shemot
b'nei Aharon.
It just says, these are the generations of אהרן Aharon and משה,
Moshe, but it doesn't mention anything about משה's Moshe children in that
particular passage. It just mentions אהרן's. Aharon So why? אלא לומר לך:
אהרן ילד ומשה לימד, לפיכך נקראו על שמו. ela lomar lecha: Aharon
yalad u'Moshe limed, lefikach nikru al shmo. So
משה Moshe taught them Torah, therefore they're called after him.
וכן הוא אומר: שם v'chen hu omer: shem God said to בית
יעקב *Beis Yaakov* that that אשר פדה אברהם *asher padah Avraham*, what
does אברהם *Avraham* do over here? He that redeemed אברהם *Avraham*. So
how so?
He freed אברהם *Avraham*, right? וכי היכן מצינו ביעקב שפדהו לאברהם *V'chi
heichan matzinu b'Yaakov she'pado l'Avraham*? What, where do we find that יעקב
*Yaakov* redeemed אברהם *Avraham*? What do you mean יעקב *Yaakov* redeemed אברהם
*Avraham*? אמר רב יהודה שפדאו מצר גידול בנים *Amar Rav Yehuda she'pado
m'tza'ar gidul banim*. So יעקב *Yaakov* sort of, if you will, like
freed אברהם *Avraham* from the task of having to have so many
children. I mean אברהם *Avraham* did have other children, but at least
12 שבטים *Shevatim* because God promised אברהם *Avraham* you're going to have
many, many, many kids, right? How many kids did he have from
שרה *Sarah*? Just one. So like, you know, so it's as if
יעקב *Yaakov* sort of bore that responsibility. So now, you know, so
these are kids that אברהם *Avraham* didn't have. So like, you know,
so now it's viewed that יעקב *Yaakov* redeemed אברהם *Avraham*. So
saved him from the trouble. So therefore they're viewed as
if לא עתה יבוש יעקב *Lo ata yeivosh Yaakov*, that's why it
says later, yeah יעקב *Yaakov* will לא יבוש *lo yeivosh*, will not
be embarrassed, ashamed. לא עתה יבוש יעקב מאביו *Lo ata yeivosh Yaakov
me'aviv*. Who's he going to be embarrassed from? His father, יעקב *Yaakov*
wouldn't have to be ashamed because of his father, his father יצחק
*Yitzchak*. ולא עתה פניו יחוורו מאבי אביו *V'lo ata panav yeichavaru me'avi
aviv*. That's the end of the פסוק *pasuk*, from his grandfather. Anyway
the point is that's why אברהם *Avraham* and יעקב *Yaakov* and all
that are in the same פסוק *pasuk* from יעקב *Yaakov* having, you
know, saved אברהם *Avraham* from this trouble. So
I'm going to try to let me just, I'm going to try
to, I do have to leave but I'm going to just try
to get a little bit at least I'm going to finish this
דף daf *daf*. So, okay now דוד *David* was married to these
daughters of שאול *Shaul*, right? Or maybe, sort of, right? I think
depending on who we're talking about, right?
So anyway, שאול *Shaul*, one of them was פלטי בן ליש Palti
ben Laish *Palti ben Layish*. Now we're going to talk about that.
כתיב פלטי וכתיב פלטיאל *K'siv Palti u'chesiv Paltiel*. Not a big deal,
but we're trying to figure out what his name is. אמר ר׳
יוחנן למה נקרא שמו פלטיאל *Amar Rabbi Yochanan lamah nikra shemo Paltiel*?
Which one is it? פלטי *Palti* or פלטיאל *Paltiel*? It's both, same
person, שפלטו א-ל *she'pelato E-l*. And, you know, and
whatever the word is, an anagram, שפלטו א-ל *she'pelato E-l*. God saved
him, פלט *palat*, you know, פלט *palat* is to save, like you
know, God saved him from an עבירה *aveirah*. Meaning God saved this
פלטי בן ליש Palti ben Laish. *Palti ben Layish* from an עבירה
*aveirah*. What would be the עבירה *aveirah*? Sleeping with a married woman,
right? That's according at least according to this that she was married
to דוד *David*. So how did that work? How was he saved?
Remember, you know, back then like they didn't have extra beds. They
had to sleep in the same bed. So מה עשה נעץ חרב
בינו לבינה *Mah asah? Na'atz cherev beino l'veinah*. He, they slept in
the bed but he put a sword between the two of them.
So, you know, anyone who rolls over, you know, would be kind
of, you know, cut by the sword. אמר כל העוסק בדבר זה
ידקר בחרב זה *Amar: kol ha'osek b'davar zeh yidaker b'cherev zeh*. Whoever
will, you know, do this, in other words whichever one of us
comes to the other to, you know, have relations, will be pierced
with this sword.
But what do you mean he never had relations with her? But
doesn't it say
that וילך אתה אישה *vayeilech itah ishah*? You know, this is
when they said all right give me my wife already, you know,
then all right, you know, this is over. So then it says
her husband walked with her. So if they never were married, what
do you mean her husband?
So, אשתה
דלה היא *ishta d'lah hi*. Like, you know, he viewed her as
his wife. He never actually, you know, slept with her. בכה וילך
אחריה עד בחורים *Bacho v'yeilech achareiah ad Bachurim*. So what was he
crying about? וילך אחריה *vayeilech achareiah*, she was never his wife, so
what was he crying about? Well because, you know,
according to this על מצוה דאזלא מיניה *al mitzvah d'azla mineih*. He
was overcoming such temptation, it's such a great מצוה *mitzvah* for not
sleeping with her, that's what he was crying about, not because he
was losing her, but you know, he was losing the opportunity to
do this מצוה *mitzvah* of not being with her. So
and then it says עד בחורים *ad Bachurim*. So he went to
בחורים *Bachurim*. בחורים *Bachurim* is a place but you could say you
know they went שנעשו שניהם כבחורים שלא טעמו טעם ביאה *she'na'asu sheneihem
k'vachurim shelo ta'amu ta'am bi'ah*. They're like youths that they never had
relations with each other. They're like you know, single people. אמר ר׳
יוחנן תוקפו של יוסף ענוותנותו של בועז Boaz *Amar Rabbi Yochanan: tokpo
shel Yosef anvetanuso shel Boaz*. So יוסף *Yosef* had a trial but
that was like easy stuff for בועז *Boaz*. וענוותנותו
של בועז *V'anvetanuso shel Boaz*, sorry, תוקפו של בועז ענוותנותו של פלטי
*tokpo shel Boaz anvetanuso shel Palti*. And then בועז *Boaz*'s trial was
like easy stuff for פלטי בן ליש *Palti ben Layish*. What do
we mean תוקפו של יוסף ענוותנותו של בועז *tokpo shel Yosef anvetanuso
shel Boaz*? So remember יוסף *Yosef* was just with a woman who
wasn't his, it was just his master's wife, and this was somebody
else's wife, right? And just
like a one-time thing, right?
So and so there's a married woman. But so that was like,
you know, that's like not easy, but that was nothing compared to
בועז *Boaz*. דכתיב ויהי בחצי הלילה ויחרד האיש וילפת *d'chsiv v'yehi bachatz
h'lailah vayecherad ha'ish vayilafes*. בועז *Boaz* had a single woman, Ruth, over
there in the night, right? So he could have, you know, wouldn't
have been an עבירה *aveirah* so to speak. It says ויחרד האיש
וילפת *vayecherad ha'ish vayilafes*. So he, you know, he trembled,
startled, whatever you want to say. וילפת *Vayilafes*. What does that mean?
It's
a very strange word. So now what are we explaining that as
meaning?
מאי וילפת *Mai vayilafes*? אמר רבא שנעשה בשרו כראשי לפתות *Amar Rava
she'na'asa b'saro k'roshei l'fasos*. So
his his skin or really, you know, a certain area of his
skin. So בועז's and ומה של פלטי בן ליש u'ma shel Palti
ben Laish and the trial of בועז was like nothing of פלטי
בן ליש because כדאמר kidi'amar like we were saying, that was just
one night with a single woman and this was like, you know,
this was every night. So so you know, so that goes to
show you the greatness of פלטי בן ליש. Oh we got to
stop. All right, so this will continue
tomorrow
and where we should be at least we're not a דף daf
behind them. We're not a דף daf behind. No wait, we're never
a דף daf behind, the only question was where were we going
to be a דף daf ahead. Oh I see. This is where
we should be. Okay. I think אריה Aryeh will do tomorrow. Yeah
you know what, I'll just do it, I prepared all this דף
anyway. I'll do what? I'll do it, I'll tell him. I mean
I prepared it, so you know. Tomorrow you mean? Yeah why not,
I did it anyway. Right, because you prepared it, right, right, right.
Now what should we do with this, should we leave this on
because? Okay wait, I have to turn this thing off. How do
I turn this off? Oh you just slide that thing down. Turn
it off? Okay. Put it down until it goes off.